[Music]
this program is brought to you by
Stanford University please visit us at
stanford.edu
all right I am not going to tell you the
entire history of
cosmology we're going to get straight to
the
point the point is the expanding
universe and the geometry of the
expanding universe
well let's uh let's back off for a
minute and discuss what it is where it
is we want to
go I want to teach you the basics of
modern cosmology and the basics of
modern cosmology consist of a handful of
things uh not a
lot but of course the things which went
into the discoveries the especially the
observational discoveries iies were a
lot more than I'm going to tell you but
basically we're going to take uh you
know go to the go to the end of the
story to a large extent and say what is
it that we know now um we're going to
start with the basic Big Bang Theory
we're not going to go back in time
before there was a Big Bang Theory we're
going to start with the basic Big Bang
Theory the three possible versions of
it we're going to do it from two points
of view and then match them and see how
they relate the first is just thinking
about geometry the general theory of
relativity that we discussed last year
now we're not going to have to know very
much about the general theory of
relativity just some very very simple
things
uh and we're going to talk about
expanding space we're going to talk
about the Hubble law the Hubble law of
recession uh the relation between
velocity and distance and so forth we're
going to derive that from some simple
principles we'll State what the simple
principles of ology R of big bang
cosmology and we'll work out some
examples of expanding universes the
geometry of them not the physics of them
this is the geometry of them the physics
is driven by energy and
momentum and other dynamical things to
get a handle on that I don't know if
we'll do it this week but next week
either this week or next week we'll move
on to the
Newtonian f equals m a
cosmology f equals ma cosmology takes us
a long way and we're going to see some
connections some connections between the
geometry and the f equals ma version of
cosmology Newton what Newton would have
understood his cosmology then we're
going to put them together into a single
package called fredman Robertson Walker
F frw
cosmology that will take us a couple of
weeks
from
there we'll address some other
questions what is inflation what is the
inflationary theory of
cosmology what is dark energy what is
dark matter how are they
different uh the cosmological constant
which is dark energy the current
accelerated expansion of the
universe uh and then perhaps we'll move
on to some more modern esoteric struct
uh subjects
such as why do physicists think perhaps
there's much more to the universe than
can ever than than we can see but more
than we ever can see and the idea of a
Multiverse and I'm not sure what else uh
we'll fill in some details as we go
along if there are particular things you
want me to discuss I'll do it as usual
uh but let's get
started
okay let's begin
just with the idea of space in the
simplest possible space onedimensional
space for Simplicity then it will
immediately add two more Dimensions
space not space
time and it's just good old
xaxis the x-axis imagine it goes on
indefinitely both in the left Direction
and the right direction Direction and
imagine embedded in it are
some
objects which are equally
spaced they're embedded in the space and
I'm going to give them a name now
they're called
galaxies okay one-dimensional galaxies
but they're just particles or objects
which are embedded in this
line okay now the first question
question is let's let's label a line
with a coordinate and let's label a line
with a
coordinate which in this particular case
just measures
off this is xal 0 and let's use the
presence of these galaxies to define a
coordinate so that by definition the
next galaxy over is xals 1 obviously
this is an enormous uh idealization
where I have the G is perfectly
uniformly spaced this is of course not
the case in the real
world uh incidentally for those who may
wonder the world is three-dimensional
not onedimensional so that's a further
idealization or a further fiction xal 2
this is worse than flat land this is
line land here's xal
minus1 whoops
minus1 is x =
-2 and roughly speaking these these
coordinates simply label which Galaxy
we're talking about we could think of
them as the name of the
Galaxy this galaxy is called xal 2 this
one is called xal 1 they're just labels
which move with the galaxies if the
galaxies are moving if they're spreading
apart if they're for if they're coming
together this coordinate just is
attached to the
Galaxy all right now how far is
it from let's say xal 0 to x =
1 well it's some distance it's not one
unit this is these are just the names of
these points these don't say anything
about distance I'm going to assume
they're equally spaced but what is the
spacing I haven't told you what the
spacing between them is in meters or
kilometers or light years pick your
favorite unit for the time being the
units aren't
important but what's that Galaxy well
they are are one Galaxy apart if by
galaxies we mean the distance between
galaxies of the size of G well we could
use the size of each Galaxy but we could
use what well I don't want to use the
size of the Galaxy because it's going to
raise a question that I I don't but
let's say meters meter sticks we measure
them off and I'm going to call the
distance between xal 0 and x = one in
meters or whatever definite units we use
the reason I don't want to use a size of
galaxies is because the size of galaxies
changes with
time they tend to contract so I don't
want to get into that but uh just good
old meter sticks uh good solid meter
sticks that don't change with time and
let's say the distance between xal 0 and
xal 1 let's just call it
[Music]
a a that's that's it What's the diff
what's the distance between xal 0 and
xal 2 twice a
because I've assumed that they're really
equally spaced in particular the
distance between any two points is just
let's call it Delta
X that's the difference in X time
a a * the difference in X if it's x = 2
- x = 0 and it's 2 a this is the
distance between any two
galaxies Delta X means the difference of
X this could be xal let's see 1 2 3 4 5
the distance between the Galaxy called x
= 5 and the Galaxy called xal
1 that's Delta x = 4 * a is the distance
a * 4 is the same as 4 *
a what about the distance between x = 3
and x =
-1 that's also 4 *
a and so that's the notation that's the
notational thing we're going to do
distance is the coordinate
difference times a and a has a name it's
called the scale factor it's called the
scale factor it's name its name is the
scale
factor okay now the galaxies may be
moving think of this line imagine this
line for the moment as an elastic
thread an infinite elastic thread but
infinite is too big right for right now
a very large elastic thread and there
are two Giants at the end and the two
Giants are having fun with the people in
this uh in this
universe and they're pulling maybe they
all also even allow it to go the other
way they
change the total length of the uh
of the world so to
speak just by pulling on this thread and
stretching it Contracting it doing
whatever it is they decide to do mostly
stretch it but uh for the time being
what does that mean about
a that simply means that a depends on
time the distance between two
neighboring galaxies will depend on time
exactly as it would think of rubber band
cut the rubber band open don't I don't
want it to be double and think about
stretching and instead of galaxies think
about the rubber molecules you stretch
that increases the distance between um
neighboring
molecules you contract it that decreases
the distance and so in that way in
general a is a function of
time in this world with these Giants who
are pulling on the end of the string
this is not String Theory incident ly
nothing to do with string theory not yet
anyway I've heard that in
Berkeley there's a restaurant called
Noodle Theory can anybody confirm
that it's true Noodle Theory
okay okay so this is this is um the
universe and the universe is such that
first of all it is
homogeneous homogeneous means equal
spacing that's all right equal spacing
it's everywhere is the same so to speak
every one of these galaxies looks at its
neighbor and says you are a certain
number of meters away a Galaxy over here
sees the same thing as a Galaxy over
here and so forth that's the term
homogeneous everywhere is the same equal
spacing but the spacing itself imagine
that it's time
dependent okay let's now
calculate the rate at which the distance
between two galaxies grows or shrinks
the rate at which the distance changes
with time let's calculate it there's
another word for the rate at which
distance
changes what what velocity right
actually speed but the velocity Vel
right
velocity so when I say I'm calculating
the rate at which the the Galaxy at xal
4 Moves or or increases relative to xal
1 I could say it another way I'm
calculating the velocity of xal 4
relative to xal 1 but I don't just want
to call it the velocity I want to call
it the velocity of one point relative to
another all right we know what the
distance is here's the distance it's a
time Delta X now we're taking two fixed
galaxies two fixed galaxies this one
over here and this one over
here we're not going to change those
galaxies and that means that Delta X is
not going to change with time we've just
fixed the two galaxies we want to talk
about but what does change with time
a all right so what is the rate at which
D increases with
time it's just
D dot and for those who haven't been who
are new to this class dot always means
time derivative derivative with respect
to
time d by DT that's what a DOT means
derivative with respect to time I'll use
that notation and it means the rate at
which the thing is changing with time
the rate at which D is changing with
time Delta X is not increasing or or
decreasing so d
dot is Delta X that's
unchanged but a is changing with
time a
DOT the time rate of change of a product
like this if one of the factors is not
changing is just that factor times the
time derivative of the other one so this
is the rate at which
D changes with time let's call it D of
Delta X the
distance between two points separated by
Delta X that's just
this now I'm going to do oh and what do
we call this we call this the velocity
the relative
velocity between the two
points it's the
velocity that the the astronomer at xal
1 would see x = 5 moving away from him
or moving toward him it's also the
velocity that x = 5 would see of X1
either moving away or coming uh
closer it depends on whether the
derivative is positive or negative
whether they're growing larger or dist
uh less where they're approaching or
receding all right so let's write this
and now I'm going to
write a totally unnecessary uh step I'm
going to divide this and multiply it by
a
physicists and mathematicians are always
dividing and multiplying by the same
thing and you think why bother well
let's look at
it here's a * Delta x what is
that that's
D okay so I can rewrite
this as a DOT over
a that's the ratio of the rate of change
of a to a itself times the
distance now I've discovered something
interesting the velocity of
recession well I haven't discovered
anything interesting yet but uh I will I
will have discovered something
interesting in a
moment does a DOT and a depend on which
galaxies I'm talking
about no a and a DOT are the same for
every Galaxy a in particular a is just
the distance between neighboring
galaxies but it doesn't depend on which
Galaxy we're talking about so a is the
same for
everybody the scale factor it's a
universal idea which everybody agrees
about what the distance to his neighbor
is all right it changes with time but a
a do/ a does not depend on X it doesn't
depend on which Galaxy we're talking
about and what this equation then says
is the velocity between two
points is proportional to something
which does not depend on which Galaxy
we're talking about a do over a we're
going to give it another name in a
moment times the distance between
them anybody know what the name of the
of a do over a
is the Hub
constant the Hubble constant velocity is
proportional to distance is what this
says with a number in there a DOT over
a now is this necessarily constant if
the universe is expanding and
Contracting or doing whatever the devil
these Giants have decided to do is a do
over a a constant no it changes with
time right but it doesn't change with
position
position it's a constant in the sense
that it's the same everywhere but it is
not a constant in the sense that it does
not depend on time so the Hubble
constant the thing which people I prefer
to call it the Hubble parameter calling
it constant makes you think it's like um
the electric charge of an electron or
something else like that that it really
doesn't depend on anything no the Hubble
constant is a function of time but it's
not a function of which Galaxy we're
talking about all right so what does it
say it simply says the further apart two
galaxies are by that I mean further
apart in real distance the faster they
will be moving apart I say apart but
again I could be more talking about
coming together and the factor of
proportionality is the Hubble
constant where among other things it's
it says that if you look out if an
observer over here looks out to more
distant galaxies the further away he
looks the faster you will be seeing them
move if he looks at his closest
neighbor he'll see him moving away from
him perhaps at a certain rate if he
moves at the second if he looks at the
second nearest neighbor he will see him
moving a little bit faster if you see
the third nearest neighbor he will see
him moving yet faster the first further
away he looks the faster that will be
moving to the
right the same is true there's nothing
in this which has focused attention on
xal 0 or xal 1 it's the relative
separation of two things which are
entirely symmetric and it's the same
everywhere so there's no notion of a
center to this
line all points are the same as every
other point but every pair of points are
increasing their distance with a
velocity that's proportional to H * d
That's the Hubble law now there's
nothing
especially one-dimensional about this
let's do it in more Dimensions all any
questions about the about the meaning of
this
formula yeah uh if the galaxies are far
enough apart then they are going faster
in the Ste L
right that will play a very important
role in uh in
cosmology right what you're saying is
correct
um and we will come back to that for
sure it's one of the most important
things okay one other
thing if these again Alice and Bob this
is Alice's Galaxy this is Bob's
Galaxy Alice and Bob are sending each
other messages with light waves or
whatever the faster Bob moves off to the
right the more doppers shift again
they're sending their messages with
standard message senders made in the
same Factory of exactly the same kind so
they're sending light if you like uh of
a very very definite frequency in their
own reference frame
but by the time it gets from Alice's
signal by the time it gets to Bob the
Doppler shift will have rened that light
or yes rened it if I I'm always going to
assume from now on that everything is
being stretched and not contracted at
least for the
moment
so
Bob will detect Alice's message being
slowed
down but Al Alice will also detect Bob's
message being slowed down everything is
entirely symmetric between
them uh and it's simply the problem of
two people moving apart from each other
sending P sending light rays the faster
they move apart the more red shifted the
signal will be
so uh that's a fact about an expanding
Universe the further you are away the
faster you move and the faster you move
the more Doppler shifted will messages
now the kind of messages that we really
have in mind of
course
is uh messages which are sent at
frequencies which are determined by
basic underlying physics the underlying
physics might be transitions of atoms
from one energy level to another energy
level spectral lines spectral lines are
good standard uh frequency or wavelength
um
uh what should we call them they have
very definite wavelengths in their own
frame of reference and so for example if
Bob is send or Alice is sending Bob a
particular spectral line from the sodium
uh from some sodium there uh uh
transition that will be sent in his
frame of reference at the usual
frequency of a sodium line but by the
time it gets the Bob over here it will
be rened or lowered in
frequency one way that Alice can measure
the distance to Bob is by monitoring the
frequency of the light or the spectral
lines that come from Bob's
Galaxy the faster he moving
away the
uh uh the more ridden the frequency will
be so that gives you a tool now we're
not going to SP spend very much time
talking about
observation but that gives you a
tool or gives Alice a tool for measuring
the velocity of recession of any Galaxy
okay that's velocity how about the
distance to any Galaxy are there various
ways are there ways of measuring the
actual distance to a Galaxy well let me
give you a very simple what what more or
less what hubbles actually
did Hubble estimated in his first round
of detections his method for estimating
the distance to a Galaxy was very simple
if the Galaxy was bright and big in the
sky it was close if it was small and dim
it was
far uh the dimness of a
given uh size object well from the size
in the sky and from the brightness he
could estimate the
distance for reasons unknown to anybody
Hubble decided to plot on a
plot the
distance of a given Galaxy that he could
see in the sky again pretty much just
from the size of it there are much more
sophisticated ways of measuring distance
than just by size and uh and uh
brightness
but that's clearly one way to measure
the distance and on the vertical axis he
measured the
velocity of the galaxies well first of
all the first thing he discovered is
that all of the distant galaxies now
distant to Hubble doesn't mean what we
would call distant galaxies today Hubble
when was Hubble when when did Hubble do
with these wonderful things in the 20s
sometime uh um not 1820 1920 20 G
or he used galaxies yeah oh it's an
interesting historical fact that uh up
until let's see when was it I'm not
exactly sure again it was Hubble
probably
1920 or something and then 1917 1916 I'm
not sure when exactly the idea of a
galaxy didn't
exist uh all we knew about was one bunch
of stars the Milky Way across the sky
and people spoke of an island universe
that we lived in an island of stars with
nothing out further than that they did
discover that there were these blotchy
things out there but it was not
recognized that those blotchy things
were other Island universes so to speak
it wasn't really until sometime in the
uh in the middle of the early TW 20th
century that uh that Hubble realized
that what he was seeing when he saw
these smudges in the sky were
collections of stars that they were
collections of huge numbers of stars
which rivaled in size and number of
stars the Milky Way itself so that was
the first discovery the universe is
filled with
galaxies and then he as I said measured
the distance of galaxies and the
velocity of
galaxies and he discovered first thing
that surprised him the galaxies are
moving away from us apart from one or
two galaxies which are very close to us
our closest neighbor in fact just
happens to be moving toward us it's a
more or less accidental fact that it's
so close to us that it's sort of trapped
by the by our Galaxy's gravity and it
happens to be moving close uh toward us
what's the name of the closest galaxy
the Andromeda right so the Andromeda is
moving toward us
that uh is a um an more or less an
exception if you look out beyond the
Andromeda galaxy to galaxies um uh three
four five six times further away or 100
times further away they're moving away
so that was the first discovery almost
all the galaxies and in particular all
of the distant galaxies were moving away
from us furthermore they were moving
away from us by a velocity which depends
on their distance and when he plotted
it he got a perfect exact straight line
nonsense of course he didn't get it he
got a
mishmash which was all over the
place Arab bars but somehow he looked at
this and whether he was intuiting the
right answer or he was a master of
Statistics which I don't think he was or
whatever it was he drew a straight line
to it and he said
look velocity is proportional to
distance he actually didn't know why had
no idea the simple argument did not
exist it's been explained in an even
simpler
way uh than this but I this picture here
is correct
and really at the heart of the matter
but it was explained by other people
just saying look why are you surprised
that the fastest horse goes the furthest
in a race that the if you look at a
horse race expect that the fastest one
has gone the
furthest right the fastest Galaxy is
most likely to be the one that's gotten
furthest away from you but that uh that
of course is just a
um a uh it's true but this is the right
way to say it this is the right way to
say it velocity is proportional the
Hubble constant time D now Hubble was
not very good at the time at measuring
the distances to the galaxies this
wasn't his own fault he just had crude
crude tools at the
time and he measured the galaxies as
being maybe 10 times closer I think than
they actually were so his Hubble
constant was off by a bit like a factor
of
10 that had
implications let me explain
why um the bigger the Hub
that of course meant that the Hubble
constant was too big too big or too
small
uh wait he measured which way did he
measure it reciprocal the time he
measured the Hubble constant being too
too big as I remember yeah he measured
the Hubble constant being too big by a
factor of 10 now that meant that his
estimate for example of this galaxy
moving away was 10 times too big
uh not that the velocity velocity was
correct but the but the estimate of the
Hubble constant itself was 10 times too
big it took a while to correct it we're
going to interpret we're going to
discover another interpretation of the
Hubble constant it's basically one over
the age of the Universe I will tell you
why later not right now so he had
misestimated the age of the universe by
a factor of
10 what's that it's really hard to tell
far it's really hard to tell how more
sophisticated tools came into play but
he misestimated things by a factor of 10
but corrected them later he he corrected
them in any case that's the Hubble law
it's very very Central I said we can
also do the same thing with more
Dimensions let's take two Dimensions
instead of one dimension just for
Simplicity X and Y and again make a
grid of course it's nonsense to say that
the galaxies are at the corners of the
grid but uh
but that's an extreme idealization but
let's imagine galaxies at the corners of
the grid then every Galaxy is labeled
with two names a first name and a last
name X and
Y and X and Y stick with the Galaxy X
and Y of a galaxy doesn't change with
time it just is it's just a label that
labels the Galaxy but the distance
between
neighbors is again called
a in both directions ah that brings up
an interesting question why is it do we
know do we know that the separation
between galaxies in this grid
model uh we could ask how do we know
that the separation between galaxies
along the x-axis is the same as the
separation between galaxies along the Y
AIS do we know what do we know about it
well
supposing the galaxies were not equally
spaced or not not that they were they
were equally spaced but they were more
crowded in the X Direction and they were
in the y
direction at the corners like
that when we look down into when we look
out into the sky we would discover that
things are different along the Y AIS
than they are along the x-axis we look
out Ong the x-axis and see very crowded
galaxies we look along the Y AIS and
discover they were very very
separated we
don't we see the same distribution of
galaxies pretty much in every direction
in the sky there's a principle involved
that it's not a principle it's a it's
it's actually just a name for that fact
it is called the isotropy of the
universe two basic names theom hity of
the
universe that means everywhere is the
same now this is everywhere is the same
at least on a scale larger than the
distance between these galaxies looked
at on a bigger scale we would say every
place is the same as every other place
everybody has a couple of neighbors
around them and that's all and every
place is the same as every other place
this here is also
homogeneous this place is is the same as
this place or has the same properties as
this place over
here this one is the same as this one
there's no sense in which this one over
here is special no different than that
one no different than that
one but there is something different
about this than
this it has to do with angles in the sky
rather than
positions it's not isotropic it isn't
the same in every Direction it's the
same in every place but it isn't the
same in every direction there's a
directionality to this a directional
bias when we look in the sky we don't
see different things in different
directions of course that's not entirely
true I mean when I look up I see
something different than when I look
down uh when I look on a scale of our
galaxy if I look into the plane of the
Galaxy I see the Milky Way if I look out
of the plane of the Galaxy I see a much
darker
Sky uh but on a scale bigger
than
uh uh a few hundred galaxies on a scale
bigger than a few hundred galaxies the
sky looks the same in every direction so
the principle is called
homogeneity and
isotropy
now how well do we really know that the
universe is or how well did Hubble or
the people at that time really know that
the Universe was
homogeneous and the answer is not very
well at all they looked they were able
to look through telescopes only to a
minute fraction of what we can see today
so really there was no good reason to
believe that the Universe was
homogeneous on scales much bigger than
they could see nevertheless all cosmy
IST assumed it and it turned out to be
essentially
correct uh that the universe is
homogeneous and isotropic same in every
direction same in every place that makes
life simple much simpler than if it was
just randomly uh different in different
places okay where were we yeah let's
come back now to two
dimensions and the spacing of galaxies
along the x-axis and the y- axis the
grid size is the same What's the diff
what's the distance between two
galaxies separated by distance Delta X
along the x axis and Delta y along the Y
AIS okay
if anybody uh want to shoot at it what
the this distance square root
of this is Pythagorean
theorem well
first of all what's the distance along
the
x-axis it's a * Delta
X the distance along the Y AIS in other
words if we took two galaxies one over
here and one over here this is the dist
the dist what's that still a Time the
distance yeah a * the Delta x no I
mean the the whole thing just magnifies
by a yeah yeah yeah yeah that's right
but let's let's write it down anyway
let's go through the steps the distance
along the x axis is a * Delta X the
distance along the Y AIS is a * Delta Y
and then using the Pythagorean theorem
the distance between them is just D is
equal to the Square t of Delta
x^2 * a^ 2 + Delta y^ 2 * a 2 and now we
can Factor the a s out of the square
root and again as Michael says it's just
proportional to
a it's proportional to a the distance
and now instead of just simply Delta X
it's the square root of Delta x^2 plus
Delta y^2 what would happen if there was
a third
dimension plus Delta
z^2 that's three-dimensional Pythagoras
Theorem which I don't know if Pythagoras
knew or if if you didn't
know okay that's the distance what's the
velocity between these two points one
over here and one out here
somewhere it's just the time derivative
of this all right so the
velocity is given by the same square
root which I won't bother to write times
the time derivative of
a a
DOT that's the velocity of recession and
now we just multiply it and divide it by
a a over a same trick as before and
recognize that a * the square root is
just the
distance so we get exactly the same
formula as
before distance times Hubble constant
the Hubble constant doesn't depend on
Direction it doesn't depend on where you
are but it does depend on time in
general it may it may depend on time
velocity equals distance time Hubble
constant and it doesn't depend on the
dimensionality of
space okay that that's the Hubble
law and as I said it's
uh an extremely simple
idea now let's talk about the geometry
of
space just one question for a minute of
the and you may get to this later but
this is always bothered me about the
sort of thing so so the velocity is H
constant time the distance this means
the distance actually is increasing the
velocity is increasing so Bob and Alis
are both being accelerated within our
model but neither one of them perceives
that the velocity is not
well you don't know whether the velocity
is increasing with time what you can say
is the velocity
increases with distance all
right but here's a possibility the
velocity of all of these
um
yeah whether the velocity of a
given Galaxy is increasing or decreasing
relative to us depends on how a is
changing with
time for example let's take a simple uh
possibility supposing a was simply
proportional to
time the distance between two
neighboring galaxies is just increasing
with time with some velocity some
particular velocity uh let's let's just
call it
t velocity one right a was proportional
to
T that's just each link here in this
lattice of galaxy is increasing linearly
with time okay what how does the
velocity what is the velocity between
these two
points
DT delta T DT I Delta a the distance
between them is
a and the velocity is just d a DT which
is one well I don't want it to be one
because one stands for the speed of
light and uh let's let's say a half or a
quarter a quarter t supposing a was
increasing like a quarter T that's a
perfectly good
law then the velocity between the two
neighbors here is just one quarter and
it stays one quarter for all time it
doesn't change but what's the velocity
between this point and this
point twice the velocity between the
neighboring
points so it's 1
12 the velocity
increases with respect to looking at
more and more distant
neighbors but it may or may not increase
with time the
velocity with time the velocity between
any two galaxies here's another example
supposing
a
increased like uh
t^2
the distance between this Galaxy and
this galaxy is increasing like t^2 what
is the velocity between
them
2T the velocity is just 2T in this case
the velocity between these two galaxies
is increasing with
time all right in any case it increases
with
distance depending on the details of how
a depends on time the
galaxies may be accelerating away from
each other or even decelerating for
example supposing a let's take another
law
well let's take the law a goes like e to
the minus
t is that a good law no that's not a
good
law uh
L okay let's take log uh yeah let's take
log T good thank you that was good log
T what is the what is the velocity
between these two neighboring
points the velocity between them is the
derivative of log T which is 1 /
T in this case the velocity is
decreasing with time as time gets bigger
the velocity is decreasing that would be
saying that they're decelerating
relative to each other other so you can
have acceleration you can have
deceleration but always the Hubble law
is correct as a function of
distance
okay that's the basic Hubble law and is
the basic fact that uh that all else is
built on
the you know it used to be
thought that the Universe was
decelerating the reason was very simple
uh well it was thought that gravity was
pulling the universe together if gravity
was pulling the universe together think
about it starting expanding gravity
would slow it down just like gravity
slows down this pin as it's going up and
will eventually turn it around it was
thought that the Universe was expanding
but that the pull of gravity was pulling
things back together and therefore
decelerating it that's what was thought
to be the case we now know that that's
not the case and the universe is
expanding at an accelerated rate okay
the everything is accelerating away from
us rather than moving with a uniform uh
velocity
okay other
questions again one yeah how do you how
do you set the initial value of a I mean
since it's
changing well you pick yeah that's a
good question but you pick some
particular time at any time
uh the initial value of a is somewhat
arbitrary
um it's not really the initial value of
a it's at which particular time do we
set a equal to some or do we do we
measure a it doesn't matter you'll
always get the same answer and uh the re
you might worry about
uh when the the particular details how
they affect the Hubble constant I think
you're asking what you're asking about
is
supposing you called this distance 2 a
or
3A would you get a different answer for
the Hub just by name you just gave it a
different name instead of the scale
factor being the distance between these
two galaxies let's take it to be the
distance out to 1/3 of the way to the
the next galaxy we could do that all
right so we would have another Hubble
constant sorry another scale factor
which was bigger or smaller it doesn't
matter than our original Hubble our
original scale factor but the ratio of a
do to a would be the same for example
supposing I defined another scale factor
let's call it
b b is 3 *
a just another definition for the scale
factor uh so that it's three times
bigger than the original definition of
it all right what about B dot over
B you might get worried you might think
you get a different answer for the
Hubble constant but you don't you get 3
a DOT over 3
a threes
cancel
so what matters really is not the scale
Factor itself but how it's changing
that's the important thing how it
changes not its overall magnitude but
we'll come back to that it's really a
question of
units the scale factor would be
different numerically if we measured in
meters or if we measure it in kilometers
and so forth and it would be different
if we chose a different time at which
we
uh no it wouldn't be different
yeah what I said is right okay let's
talk about geometry a little bit the
geometry of SpaceTime but first the
geometry of space the geometry of space
and
SpaceTime is determined by a
metric the metric in exactly the same
sense as we talked about last
quarter I'll try to be self-contained
for those who weren't here last
quarter
let's start with a very simple geometry
again a one-dimensional
geometry but uh for some for fun let's
change it a little bit not the infinite
straight
line but let's take oh let's let's first
consider the infinite straight line yeah
we have our coordinate X and we have
that the distance between any two points
is Delta x *
[Music]
a let's think of that in terms of a
metric remember what a metric is a
metric is an expression for the distance
between two very close
points when the points are close we can
replace this Delta X by the symbol
DX same thing except when small
magnitudes are small we replace them by
calculus notation a * DX that's the
distance between
uh two neighboring points right and
what's the square of the distance
between two neighboring points let's
call it DS
squar that's equal to a 2 * dx^
well that tells us something about the
metric the metric is just the co
definition of the metric the definition
of the metric of a onedimensional space
this is a very simple case of a
one-dimensional
space the metric is just a
squ all right it's a thing that
multiplies dx^ s to find the distance
squared s here stands for distance of
course
because wait a minute s isn't distance s
is yes s s is distance space spatial
distance d s squ there a^2
dx2 okay if a is changing with time
then the metric is changing with
time but still this is just a
one-dimensional space with a metric and
that metric might depend on time okay so
you see where we're going we're starting
to talk about geometry of spaces
one-dimensional spaces are too simple to
have an interesting uh curvature or
anything like that the metric of space
is just the coefficient out here we
could write that as
gxx
dx2 and what would gxx be it would just
be a
s So eventually we're going to want to
connect up the idea of the expanding
Universe with a metric of SpaceTime but
we'll come to that let's
uh
good now what about proper time remember
what proper time is proper
time D to^
squ that is equal
to dt^ 2 this is the proper time along a
trajectory let's now
imagine that what we're talking about is
space time time let's draw space
time here's space
time x and
t right our galaxies are not changing
with
X but wait a minute they are moving
further and further apart so how can I
possibly decide to draw them as if they
were all parallel like this this looks
like they're all at the same distance
forever and ever
that is where the scale the time
dependent scale factor comes in remember
that the distance between these
neighboring points is not just Delta X
it's a * Delta X and that changes with
time
now what is the proper what is the
proper time along the trajectory let's
say of a particle between two
neighboring
points the proper
time what do we call it d^
s that's equal to dt^
2 minus the square of the spatial
distance between
them what's the spatial
distance a 2
dx2 right the square of the spatial
distance between these two
points
is a^ s DX
s not just the X squ because X isn't
really spatial distance it's just a
label which is labeling these points you
could have given them different names
Fred Harry Joe Nancy whatever you like
but we gave them names which were xal 1
xal 2 x = 3 x = 4 the fact that X
doesn't change for a particular G galaxy
is the same fact as your name doesn't
change with time that doesn't mean that
the distance between you between Fred
and Harry doesn't change with time Fred
and Harry are their names the distance
between them is governed by both the
diff difference of X and the scale
factor a all right so here is our
formula now for the proper time along a
trajectory it's not just DT s now T here
is time measured by clocks moving along
here ordinary clocks moving with these
Galaxy with this
galaxy if x didn't change if we were
talking
about observations along a
Galaxy in other words moving with a
Galaxy we wouldn't have any DX squ and
we would just say the proper time was
the ordinary time but if a point is
moving through the galaxies from one
point to another then we would say that
the proper time is d^ squ minus a^ 2 dx^
2 all right this becomes the spatial
distance and a may depend on
time so another way of thinking about
the scale
factor is that it's the space component
of the metric let's just compare that
with the to^ squ well I I need need to
compare
it here's a geometry It's A Spacetime
geometry and what is its
metric its metric again is a set of
components the set of components
represents the coefficients in this form
here the dt^ squ has a
one and the space
minus minus a s
0 0 the zeros represent the fact that in
this formula there could be terms but
there aren't with DT * DX and DX X DT so
there are no off diagonal terms and this
is the geometry now this is
the general relativity
description of this expanding space the
general relativity description of the
expanding space going back to last
quarter is that a certain component of
the metric the space component of the
metric is changing with
time that's the way you describe a
geometry which is either being stretched
or contracted if the geometry is being
stretched then this component of the
metric call this
gxx gxx is min - a^ 2 it is it is the
thing which changes with time as the
universe changes its size or as the
universe changes its scale factor scale
factor and space space component of the
metric are the same thing the same is
true in three dimensions or two
Dimensions or however many dimensions
the only difference
being that the
metric would contain more
terms minus a 2 d y^ 2 minus a 2 dz^2
the X2 plus the y^2 + D z^2 this is just
the Pythagorean theorem again but now
multiply by a s so we would have a
metric which would have a one in the
time time component and a minus a 2 - A
2 - A 2 and zero everywhere else that
would be the metric of an ex a uniform
not uniformly of an expanding space with
a scale factor that was a function of
time so another way to say expanding
universe or Contracting universe is that
the metric of
space is time
dependent in other words it's a special
case of uh general relativity uh metric
of SpaceTime where the components of the
metric change with time
a growing with time expanding a
shrinking with time
Contracting all right so that connects
then this idea
of uh the time dependence of the
separation between galaxies with the
basics of uh of einsteinian geometry if
you like and all three A's in that
Matrix are the same function because of
homogeneity and
good uh
yeah let me let me make a a slightly
finer distinction they're not dependent
on position because of homogeneity
they're not dependent on Direction all
right the fact that they don't depend on
position moving around in X as opposed
to T they could depend on T but they
don't depend on X that's
homogeneity the fact that all three are
the same that's is
tropy okay that the differ the three
directions all look the same that's what
says that these three are the same the
fact that everything is the same from
place to place says that a depends
possibly depends on time does depend on
time but does not depend on position and
space so it's an extremely simple
metrical
geometry where all of the coefficients
are independent of position and space
space and isotropic meaning the the
three are the same but time dependent
time dependent but not space dependent
and not angle dependent or not axis
dependent all right
now that
uh incidentally question yeah I think
I'm a little confused are are we not
supposed to think of DX is a distance
yes DX is not the
a * DX is the
distance it's just a label it labels the
galaxies if you like here's the way to
think about it there's a bunch of
galaxies out there let's
let's and at some particular time it
doesn't really matter when but at some
particular time somebody drew a
coordinate grid through
them and now the rule is the coordinate
grid follows the galaxies as the
galaxies
expand uh there's a Galaxy over here
there's a Galaxy over here there's a
Galaxy over here the coordinate mesh
follows the galaxies all right that
means the distance between here is not
Delta X Delta X is always the same
between these two galaxies by
definition because this coordinate grid
follows the
galaxies okay the distance is a * Delta
X
that that would be the answer in meters
or kilometers or something which one
between two galaxies the distance in
light years would be a * Delta X that's
right as opposed to Delta X that's right
that's right Delta X is dividing by c s
obvious
yeah I'm going
to put the units of distance into
DX
so you could
you could put the units of distance into
X but I choose not to I put the the the
units of distance into
a yeah that's that's arbitrary that's an
arbitrary decision on my part whether I
want to put the units of distance into X
or into a a product of a * X of units of
meters so should we think of it as a DX
s is that yeah ax2 that's the same as a
SX
yeah yeah yeah the metric coefficient
for time is equal to one is that just by
convention also
uh that is a
convention not a there's no there's no
physics in that um supposing I changed
it let's change it now what is not a
convention is that the coefficient
doesn't depend on position but it could
depend on time
so let's suppose that it
was T SAR dt^ 2 just for fun
okay just for fun let's suppose that we
had t^2 dt^
2 this can be written another
way T
DT squared
right
I'm going to put a four here just
because uh you'll see why in a
moment that's twice T dt^
SAR what's twice D
tdt it's also the same
as dt^ 2^
squared the differential change in
t^2 is DT
squ
in other words whatever is
here it can be written how to say this
right you can always change
variables given a thing like this you
can always change variables to a new
definition of time where this becomes
just dt^
s if it's not dt^ squ you can find a new
change of variables of time variable
where it becomes dt^ s yeah I I think
there's another possib question about
whether there should be c^2 dt^ 2
oh yeah you're using
C well I would put the C squ over here
or put it over
there but you can also absorb it into
the scale
factor you can absorb it into the scale
factor if you like so that's a but my
rules are going to be C equals 1 one
Lighty year per year okay that's the
speed of light one unit in light years
per
year light years per year is not such a
bad unit for uh for
astronomy if you put this into
Einstein's general theory yes field
equations what do you get for uh for the
energy momentum Vector well so far wait
wait wait wait be careful all right
couple of uh Corrections energy momentum
tensor yeah no that's a good
question uh
and this is something we're going to
spend a lot of time with so let's not do
it now that's right right this is a
metric you could uh say you can put it
into Einstein's equations remember that
Einstein's equations have on the left
hand side something that involves just
the metric and on the right hand side
has the energy momentum
density or the mass density or whatever
energy momentum Mass all the same stuff
on the right hand side energy and
momentum so if we put in this
geometry we could calculate what kind of
energy momentum distribution we would
have to have in order to in order that
it solves Einstein's equations so we're
going to come to that that's a very
important part of the whole thing but
for the moment for now we're just doing
geometry and not
Dynamics Dynamics is what determines how
the metric changes with time geometry is
just the abstract description of a space
or space
time okay so an expanding universe is
one where the space components of the
metric change with time and given the
homogeneity and isotropy of the universe
a is not a function of position and it
doesn't depend on which direction we're
talking about
basic
uh rules of cosmology and they're not
absolute
rules uh in the sense that one could
discover it's inconceivable that when
will discover that the universe is not
isotropic in fact it's not exactly
isotropic it's certainly not exactly
isotropic in different directions you
actually do see slight
differences uh it's certainly not
homogeneous it's not the same here as it
is uh uh a light year away from here so
it's certainly not not exactly
homogeneous it's not exactly
isotropic and we could discover in
principle that the universe is fairly
far from is isotropic and uh and
homogeneous thus far we've made no such
Discovery and I think it's unlikely that
we will because I think we've seen about
as much as the universe as we're ever
going to
see um the universe is bigger than the
portion we can see
and it's bigger than the portion we can
ever see so we don't know that on
distant scales bigger than we can see we
obviously don't know very much we don't
know if the universe is homogeneous
isotropic on those very large scales but
it has turned out that over the size and
scales of the universe that we can
measure astronomically or by whatever
means uh the universe is isotropic and
homogeneous apart from local variations
on small
scales you know it's kind of like uh uh
a farmer's field if the farmer has
planted his corn well and
accurately then on a scale
of 100 ft it looks pretty home pretty
homogeneous equally spaced rows and so
forth on the scale SC of 2 in uh it's
very non homogene homogeneous and on a
big enough scale namely a scale bigger
than the whole Farm or the whole field
it's again not
homogeneous what we know about the
universe is that on scales
between distances between galaxies 100
galaxies apart or so forth that out to
scales as far as we can see the universe
is homogeneous we don't know whether
it's homogeneous on bigger scales and we
probably will never directly be able to
find
out uh okay let's uh let's come now to
closed
geometries you said uh you never
directly find out does that imply you
think there might be an indirect way to
find out
well
perhaps I think most thinking these days
is that it's not uh homogeneous on big
enough
scales but that's certainly something
we'll talk about before we're
finished my bet very strongly is the
universe is not homogeneous on large
scales but I will never win my bet but I
will also never lose my
bet well but then you can write a
book I can only I can only write a book
if I win my bet or lose my bet I mean
you know I'd be willing to write a book
of losing a
bet that book won't be written because
for phys for basic fundamental reasons
we won't be able to see much further
than we can see
now that's called the existence of a
horizon it's a
problem but let's could you derive the
idea from Gravity to look at masses
beyond what you can see no way to tell
what's out beyond what you can
see so even the gravitational for would
be lied by see no
no if we're sitting here in this room we
are in the field of the Sun and we're
circulating around the Sun but there's
no easy way there's no way for us in
this room on this Earth without being
able to see out beyond the room to tell
that the sun is
there now we can
measure tiny tiny um tidal
forces
but the tidle forces in this room I
don't feel stretched do you feel
stretched I'm not talking about the
tidle force is due to the
Earth the certainly tidal force is due
to the earth I
feel I actually can't feel those either
if I jump off a springboard a diving
board or something something while I'm
in free fall I don't feel squeezed and
pulled and uh I can't tell that uh that
the Earth is there if I close my eyes I
could be in free fall a zillion miles
from the earth so the answer is that you
can't tell that there's a large mass out
there except by its tidal forces it only
has tidal forces if it's close enough to
you and you are big enough to feel the
variations of the gravitational field
from place to place so if there's a
large lump of mass very very far out
there we're just freely falling in the
presence of it and we don't feel it
uh as except I say through possible
tidal forces which are too small to feel
if things are far enough
away right
so the Horizon which we haven't even
begun to discuss yet is an ultimate
barrier to
um and and the frightening thing
frightening I don't know if it's
frightening frustrating frightening
fascinating thing is we know with
virtual certainty that the universe is
at least a thousand times bigger in
volume than the Horizon than we can ever
ever ever in principle ever see so we
know the stuff out there that we will
never be able to detect and we can't
tell what it is we can't tell if it's
similar to us we can't tell uh why do
you know
that that's why you took this course to
find
out uh microwave an
isotropy measurement of the
curvature but uh if I don't answer that
remind me to answer it but not now okay
let's talk about the idea of a closed
Universe now the closed Universe well
it's best described by Example The
Infinite line is an open
universe
closed and bounded I'm not sure closed
and bounded closed and
bounded the infinite line is certainly
not
bounded a line
segment like
that is
bounded has a certain size bounded means
it has boundaries it has it comes to an
end well that's not what bounded means
excuse me doesn't mean that it has
boundaries uh it just means in some
sense it's a finite extent now the
universe is not as far as we know
anything like this line it doesn't have
to be a line we could be talking about a
square or a cube a cube with
walls the universe could all be inside a
cube with
walls what does this
violate it violates homog geneity every
place is not the same as and isotropy
for the case of a cube yeah and isotropy
somebody standing right at the center
see something quite different than
somebody standing up here near the
corner number one number two even at the
center here even if you are at the
center you look in different directions
you see different things in One
Direction you see a corner in another
Direction you see a smooth face
by C I mean detect by whatever means you
can detect the shape of the universe so
a bounded
Universe seems like it's out of bounds
in the sense that if the universe is
truly isotropic and
homogeneous then uh let's concentrate on
homogeneous then it can't be a cube with
walls good okay so a sphere is an a very
interesting
case here's a
sphere the circle is good enough I mean
the interior of the circle this region
in here somebody at the center looks out
in different directions and sees the
same thing in every
direction so from his perspective or her
perspective over here the universe
appears
isotropic right but it's certainly not
homogeneous somebody over here
does not see the same thing as somebody
over here this person over here sees a
wall close to him on the right or upper
right here and far from him in the other
direction in fact this Observer over
here on this galaxy does not see an
isotropic
universe doesn't see an isotropic
Universe because this the direction is
different than that direction it's
neither it happens to be isotropic for
one one special person the person at the
center but for everybody else it looks
nonisotropic and it's certainly not
homogeneous because the properties over
here are different than the properties
over here all right so that boundary is
a uh is
a we don't know as I said that the
universe is truly on very very large
scales um isotropic and homogeneous but
let's take it as a principle in fact it
is called the cosmological principle
that the universe is isotropic and
homogeneous now uh I remember as a young
as a young
physicist being absolutely convinced
that it must be true because it's a
principle and then when you ask where
does this principle come from well we
assume it's
true so it is the cosmological principle
but it could any day of the week we
could make some radical discovery that
it is not true
I don't think it's going to happen for
reasons that you'll understand later
yeah because I isotropy everywhere
homogene yes that's a good point
isotropy everywhere implies
homogeneity in other words isotropy is
homogeneous H in other words it's
isotropy is
homogeneous if the universe is not
homogeneous then somebody will see it
being uh um and
isotropic it's genus it doesn't mean no
no no that's right that's right for
example here is a universe this is a
universe of arrows it's a universe made
of arrows and they're all pointing in
the same
direction they densely fill space let's
say that's very homogeneous just goes on
and on and on
it's homogeneous in that it's every
place the same but it's not isotropic it
has a direction associated with it
right
uh and isotropy doesn't imply
homogeneity this fellow at the center
here sees
isotropy when he looks out but this is
not
homogeneous but if
everybody sees
isotropy
if everybody sees things being the same
in every direction that happens yes to
imply homogeneity so they're not quite
independent they're two different
concepts they're related though in a
particular way yeah so if you're on the
surface of the sphere ah the surface of
the sphere that's that's that's another
thing on
a very bald sphere bald meaning
featureless every place is the same same
as every other place every direction
that you look in is the same as every
other direction that you look in on the
surface of a sphere and it's
bounded remember bounded does not mean
that it has a boundary it's now we're
talking about little creatures let's
imagine little two-dimensional creatures
flatland creatures except instead of
living on a plane they live on the
surface of a perfect
sphere and they can't look away from the
surface of the sphere they can't look
into into the sphere and the reason is
because light only travels on the sphere
itself on the surface of the sphere in
this Theory or in this world if light
only travels on the surface of the
sphere all they can do is look around
within the surface of the sphere look
that way that way that way that way and
on the surface of the sphere all
directions are the same and all places
are the same so that's basically the key
to
combining isotropy h homogenity and
boundedness again boundedness does not
mean a boundary these creatures do not
fall off the edge of the Earth when they
get to a certain point they go
around uh so boundedness does not mean
boundary it
means um
boundedness finiteness in some sense
right
okay all right the simplest
example would be life on a closed curve
for example life on a
circle okay a circle has a metric let's
talk about a life on a
circle a nice parameter a nice parameter
which could be a coordinate again there
might be galaxies sprinkled around on
this
circle every point on the circle is the
same as every other point not quite true
of course the point points between the
Galaxy are different than the points on
the galaxies but on scales bigger than
the size of a Galaxy every point is the
same as every incidentally what does
isotropy mean in one
dimension uh isotropy is clear in two
Dimensions you look in different
directions what left and right left and
right being the same that's right so
here for example is a one-dimensional
world which is homogeneous but not isot
Tropic it consists of little arrows
pointing in One Direction all along
it left is different than
right all right left is different than
right but every place is the same as
every other place so in a
one-dimensional world you can also have
an isotropy non isotropy what it means
is simply left and right along the line
are different
okay so if I just have a population of
galaxies like this on the average left
and right are the
same every point is the same as every
other point and I would say this was
homogeneous
isotropic uh and
bounded okay let's talk about the metric
let's talk about its
geometry how do we what might we
characterize the position by well we
could use x but X is an inconvenient
variable on a circle a convenient
variable on a circle is
angle so we could pick one Galaxy and
call it theta equals z Theta is my
notation for angle or at least one
possible notation for
angle and we could characterize every
other Galaxy this is theta equals z by
some
Theta and what's this galaxy over
here well we could call it
minus a negative angle or we could call
it 364
degrees it's almost all the ways around
so what did I say
364 did I say 364 oh that's the number
of days in a year D
359 sorry I got the number of days in
the year confus with the number of
degrees on a
circle
wow okay right
359° not quite all the ways around not
quite
360° okay but we could use an angle to
characterize the
position again or let's uh let's suppose
for the moment that the radius of this
circle or the circumference of it the
little bugs who live in this world have
no sense of radius because they have no
sense of where the center of it is it's
not in their world but they do have a
sense of
circumference they can measure the
circumference by marching along it till
they come back to the same place they
can measure the circumference the
circumference means
something and of course they could call
a circumference 2 pi times something if
they wanted uh uh and that's something
they might call the radius but they
would have no particular reason to but
they
could uh so they have a sense of
circumference and let's now talk about
the distance between the distance around
the circle the size of the circle uh we
can call let's
call let's see I uh let's call the total
distance around the circle do I want to
call it a or do I want to call it 2 pi *
a a I think I'll just call it a scale
factor scale factor is the total
distance
around now supposing we have let's let's
yeah why am I calling that scale factor
we'll see in a moment
but let's take the distance between two
points Theta equal 0 and Theta equal
Theta just Theta what's the distance
between those two
points a * Theta let's define it to be a
* Delta
Theta or a is not let's see we got to do
this right let's get the numbers in
there correctly we're going to measure
angles in
radians all right so the total distance
around in radians is 2 pi total distance
around is 2 pi so this point is zero and
if I go all the ways around and I come
to the point just below it that's 2 pi
radians
around okay um the to the total distance
around
is 2
pi let's call it 2 pi * a I'm going to
call it 2 pi * a where a would be the
radius if I decided to plot it as a
circle if I decided to plot now remember
these people who live on here can't tell
whether it's a circle or whether it's a
uh curve like that they have no way of
telling because they can't see into the
interior all they know is the distance
around but let's uh pretend that we drew
it as a
circle then the total distance around I
would call 2 pi * a but what's the
distance between two neighboring points
let's suppose the points were separated
by a distance Delta
Theta then the distance between them
would be a * Delta Theta the radius of
the sphere the radius of the circle
times the change in angle the distance
between two points on a circle a circle
of radius
a is a Time the angle angular
distance well this is very much like a *
Delta X X it's just I've used
Theta and Theta happens to have the
property that when you go around the
circle it comes back to itself that you
come back to yourself but otherwise this
is very much like a * Delta
X in fact we have a metric we can say
the distance between two points squared
between two neighboring points squared
is a
s d Theta
2qu so in fact we have a metric on a
circle very very similar to The Case of
the infinite straight line except now
the space is bounded it's bounded
because when Theta comes all the ways
around by 2 pi you come back to the same
place this is a closed and bounded
universe and here is its metric now this
is not a space-time metric this is just
a space
metric right
so you could imagine the creatures who
live on this thing measure this distance
around here and then they know what a is
they know what a is okay but you can
also Imagine a changing with time again
a changing with time would correspond to
the radius of this circle changing with
time in that case we would write d s s
distance between two points is a of
t^2 time D Theta squar and we might even
write A Spacetime metric we might write
D to squ the space time
metric is dt^ 2 minus a 2 AF of t^
2 D S
should should be
a line up from here one up one up right
above that a squ of t a s a of
t^2
yeah D Theta squar good
yeah yeah right all right what does this
geometry look like let's try to think
about it as A
Spacetime as a space time we'll
start the vertical axis is going to be
time let's start at one instant when a
has some particular value here's a let's
say a equals 1 or seven or something
else so it looks like a
circle that's at one particular time now
the vertical axis is the time axis as
time goes on a
changes that means let's say gets bigger
that means that the SpaceTime
geometry grows with time let's suppose
at some time it stopped growing and
turned around and shrunk started to
shrink turn
around and start to
shrink maybe it does something crazy
oscillates or starts to grow
again the surface the space time looks
like a surface and it looks like a
surface of a um it looks like a vase or
a vase whatever you call
it in fact we might even
imagine A
Spacetime which starts what would the
scale factor be at this
point if the universe
started infinitely shrunken here it is
it starts infinitely
shrunken like a circle of infinitely
small size and it starts to expand
expands out to some maximum size I'm not
taking this as seriously that it expands
out to maximum size expands out starts
to shrink again starts to grow again
does whatever it does what would be the
scale factor at this
point be a equal a equals z at that
point so in this closed and bounded
Universe a equal 0 corresponds to the
thing shrunk to zero
size
right and then it starts to grow grows
from zero and very quickly becomes
something not zero and then changes its
size maybe in and out and in and out
whatever it does whatever it does okay
so that's a geometry it's quite clear
that this geometry is
curved it's it's quite curved it's
curved in the sense of
Einstein that's a closed and bounded
this is the simplest example of a closed
and bounded Universe which also happens
to be time
dependent in this universe Hubble's Law
is still
correct for exactly the same reasons as
before the distance between two points
points again involves a * Delta
Theta distance is a Delta
Theta the velocity is a DOT time Delta
Theta and that's the same as a do a * a
Delta Theta which is Hubble constant a
do over a time
distance so Hubble's Law is still true
this the velocity between these
points uh is proportional to the
distance between them you get into a
little bit of confusion when a distance
is so large that it comes around the
other side let's forget that for a
moment but an astronomer over here
looking not too far away with SE hubbles
laow and uh that's the idea of a closed
and bounded
Universe notice that the closed and
bounded universe is not an explosion
from a point in three-dimensional space
where stuff gets ejected out it's not
like the explosion of a hydrogen bomb
where something is concentrated in space
and then goes flying out into
space it's the same
everywhere everywhere it's the same and
yet if we imagine galaxies let's imagine
galaxies or particles or
whatever here they are they're spread
out on here
they separate uh because the distance
between them gets larger they start to
come together
again they start to what happens to them
when we look way back at very early
times they're very close to each other
now let's say there are 360
galaxies those 360 galaxies are well
spread out here but they're very very
close together here here they're even
close closer
together they get too close together
they're not separate galaxies anymore
get them even closer they're not even
separate atoms anymore but notice
there's no special point in space space
Now does not mean this three-dimensional
room it means this onedimensional
closed and bounded Universe the little
bugs live on no special
place no sense of being ejected out of
some particular place like the like the
bomb explosion but instead just a
uniform rapid expansion taking place
everywhere at the same time satisfying
the Hubble law okay but things get
pretty crowded down
here infinitely crowded if the universe
began as a uh as a point so when
somebody comes and asks you well
where did the Big Bang take place where
did this big bang take place where were
all these things ejected out of the
answer is
everywhere okay so
question time is it curved that was a
cylinder say it again you say the space
time is curved would it be curved if
that were a cylinder no if it were a
cylinder it would not be curved if it
was a cylinder in other words if a were
constant with time if a were constant
with time that would be like this that
would be this
world
uh I meant cone oh good a cone is an
even yes good good cone all right all
right first of all cylinder a cylinder
is the case where a doesn't depend on
time at
all right good that's just a constant a
up and down that is not curved that's
not curved that's obviously not curved
um
no no the cylinder the space time is not
curved it's it's it looks like it's
curved because I tried to draw it in
three
dimensions but it's not curved remember
why you could take a scissors and cut it
open take a scissors cut it open without
stretching it without stretching it you
could lay it out as a on the
plane and it would be you don't have to
stretch it to lay it out on the plane
okay so that's not curved if you laid it
out on the
plane so there it
is I've cut it open laid it out on the
plane just mathematically cut cut it
open in my
imagination then the cylinder is in here
but this point and that point are the
same point in the sense that when I cut
it here this point which half of which
went with this way and half of which
went that way become these two points
which are really the same point all
right so no the cylinder is flat okay or
equivalently in this particular case for
a onedimensional universe not the same
threedimensional is different but for a
one-dimensional
universe the time independent universe
is
flat okay flat in the SpaceTime sense
now what about The Cone first of all
what does the cone correspond to it
corresponds
to there's the cone the SpaceTime cone
how does the scale factor grow with time
in the space-time cone linear
linear linear the size of the cone is
linear in the
time and you double you double the time
that means double the distance along
here you double the size of the uh all
right so that means a is proportional to
time again a quarter a fifth a tenth
whatever um the scale factor is
proportional to time is this or is this
not flat as a space
time it's not flat at the bottom that's
for sure it's got a conical Singularity
there but cones if you slice them and
open them up are flat all right so a
cone is flat you make a cone out of a
flat sheet of
paper
by I mean it's the same deal as we
studied last
time just by
sewing the edges together you make a
cone but the only place that the cone is
curved is right at the tip of the the
cone here that's the only place where
there's any real curvature so yeah this
is also flat except for the tip the tip
is the origin of time here the Big Bang
or
whatever uh we haven't gotten the Big
Bangs
yet all right
so I think I think it's time to quit now
next time we will
discuss not the circular universe but
the spherical universe or the universe
which is a three-dimensional sphere
uh and the geometry of it and then we'll
go on to discuss what is the thing which
determines How the Universe
grows what is the Dynamics which causes
it to grow or Shrink or whatever it does
and uh that will bring us
to the end of next
[Music]
week
the proceeding program is copyrighted by
Stanford University please visit us at
stanford.edu